The world is changed.
I feel it in the water.
I feel it in the earth.
I smell it in the air.
Much that once was...
...is lost.
For none now live who remember it.
It began with the forging
of the Great Rings.
Three were given to the Elves:
Immortal, wisest and fairest of all beings.
Seven to the Dwarf-lords:
Great miners and craftsmen of the mountain halls.
And nine...
...nine rings were gifted
to the race of Men...
... who, above all else, desire power.
For within these rings was bound
the strength and will to govern each race.
But they were all of them deceived.
For another ring was made.
In the land of Mordor,
in the fires of Mount Doom...
... the Dark Lord Sauron forged
in secret a Master Ring...
... to control all others.
And into this Ring he poured
his cruelty, his malice...
...and his will to dominate all life.
One Ring to rule them all.
One by one...
... the Free Lands of Middle-earth
fell to the power of the Ring.
But there were some who resisted.
A Last Alliance of Men and Elves
marched against the armies of Mordor.
And on the slopes of Mount Doom, they
fought for the freedom of Middle-earth.
Victory was near.
But the power of the Ring...
...could not be undone.
It was in this moment...
... when all hope had faded...
... that Isildur, son of the king,
took up his father's sword.
Sauron, the enemy of the Free Peoples
of Middle-earth, was defeated.
The Ring passed to Isildur...
... who had this one chance
to destroy evil forever.
But the hearts of Men...
...are easily corrupted.
And the Ring of Power
has a will of its own.
It betrayed Isildur...
... to his death.
And some things
that should not have been forgotten...
... were lost.
History became legend...
...legend became myth.
And for
two and a half thousand years...
... the Ring passed
out of all knowledge.
Until, when chance came...
...it ensnared a new bearer.
My precious.
The Ring came to the creature
Gollum...
... who took it deep into the tunnels
of the Misty Mountains.
And there it consumed him.
It came to me.
My own. My love. My own.
My precious.
The Ring brought to Gollum
unnatural long life.
For 500 years it poisoned his mind.
And in the gloom of Gollum's cave,
it waited.
Darkness crept back
into the forests of the world.
Rumor grew of a shadow in the East...
... whispers of a nameless fear.
And the Ring of Power perceived...
...its time had now come.
It abandoned Gollum.
But something happened then
the Ring did not intend.
It was picked up by the most unlikely
creature imaginable.
What's this?
A Hobbit.
Bilbo Baggins of the Shire.
A ring.
Lost!
My precious is lost!
For the time will soon come...
... when Hobbits will shape
the fortunes of all.
The 22nd day of September...
...in the year 1400...
...by Shire-reckoning.
Bag End, Bagshot Row, Hobbiton,
West farthing...
...the Shire...
...Middle-earth.
The Third Age of this world.
"There and Back Again."
A Hobbit's Tale.
By Bilbo Baggins.
Now...
...where to begin?
Ah, yes....
"Concerning...
...Hobbits."
Hobbits have been living and farming
in the four Farthings of the Shire...
...for many hundreds of years...
...quite content to ignore
and be ignored...
...by the world of the Big Folk.
Middle-earth being, after all,
full of strange creatures beyond count...
...Hobbits must seem
of little importance...
...being neither renowned
as great warriors...
...nor counted among the very wise.
Frodo! Someone at the door.
In fact, it has been remarked by some...
... that Hobbits' only real passion
is for food.
A rather unfair observation...
...as we have also developed a keen
interest in the brewing of ales...
...and the smoking of pipe-weed.
But where our hearts truly lie...
...is in peace and quiet...
...and good, tilled earth.
For all Hobbits share a love
of things that grow.
And, yes, no doubt to others,
our ways seem quaint.
But today of all days,
It is no bad thing
to celebrate a simple life.
Frodo, the door!
Sticklebacks. Where is that boy?
Frodo!
Down from the door where it began
And I must follow if I can
The road goes ever on and on
Down from the door where it began
Now far ahead the road has gone
-And I must follow if I can
-You're late.
A wizard is never late, Frodo Baggins.
Nor is he early. He arrives
precisely when he means to.
It's wonderful to see you, Gandalf!
You didn't think I'd miss
your Uncle Bilbos birthday?
How is the old rascal?
I hear it's going to be a party
of special magnificence.
You know Bilbo.
He's got the whole piece in an uproar.
Well, that should please him.
Half the Shire's been invited.
And the rest of them are turning up
anyway.
And so life in the Shire goes on...
... very much as it has
this past Age...
...full of its own comings and goings,
with change coming slowly.
If it comes at all.
For things are made to endure
in the Shire...
...passing from one generation
to the next.
There's always been a Baggins
living here under the Hill...
...in Bag End.
And there always will be.
To tell you the truth,
Bilbo's been a bit odd lateIy.
I mean, more than usual.
He's taken to locking himself
in his study.
He spends hours poring over old maps
when he thinks I'm not looking.
Where's it gone?
He's up to something.
-All right, then. Keep your secrets.
-What?
But I know you have something
to do with it.
Good gracious me.
Before you came along, we Bagginses
were very well thought of.
Indeed.
Never had any adventures
or did anything unexpected.
If you're referring to the incident
with the dragon, I was barely involved.
All I did was give your uncle
a little nudge out of the door.
Whatever you did, you've been officially
labeled a disturber of the peace.
Oh, really?
Gandalf! Gandalf!
Fireworks, Gandalf!
-Gandalf!
-Fireworks, Gandalf!
Gandalf?
-I'm glad you're back.
-So am I, dear boy.
So am I.
No, thank you!
We don't want any more visitors,
well-wishers or distant relations!
And what about very old friends?
Gandalf?
-Bilbo Baggins.
-My dear Gandalf!
Good to see you. 111 years old!
Who would believe it?
You haven't aged a day.
Come on, come in!
Welcome, welcome.
Oh, here we are.
Tea? Or maybe something
a littIe stronger?
I've got a few bottles
of the Old Winyard left. 1296.
Very good year. Almost as old as I am.
It was laid down by my father.
What say we open one, eh?
Just tea, thank you.
I was expecting you sometime
last week.
Not that it matters. You come and go as
you please. Always have and always will.
You caught me a bit unprepared. We've only
got cold chicken and a bit of pickle....
There's some cheese here.
No, that won't do.
We've got raspberry jam,
an apple tart....
But not much for afters.
Oh, no, we're all right.
I've just found some sponge cake.
I could make you some eggs
if you'd--
-Just tea, thank you.
-Oh, right.
-You don't mind if I eat, do you?
-No, not at all.
Bilbo! Bilbo Baggins!
I'm not at home!
It's the Sackville-Bagginses.
-I know you're in there!
-They're after the house.
They've never forgiven me
for living this long.
I've got to get away from these confounded
relatives, hanging on the bell all day...
...never giving me a moment's peace.
I want to see mountains again.
Mountains, Gandalf!
And then find somewhere quiet
where I can finish my book. Oh, tea.
-So you mean to go through with your plan?
-Yes, yes. It's all in hand.
All the arrangements are made.
Oh, thank you.
Frodo suspects something.
Of course he does. He's a Baggins...
...not some blockheaded Bracegirdle
from Hardbottle.
You will tell him, won't you?
-Yes, yes.
-He's very fond of you.
I know.
He'd probably come with me
if I asked him.
I think in his heart, Frodo's
still in love with the Shire.
The woods, the fields.
Little rivers.
I am old, Gandalf.
I know I don't look it, but I'm
beginning to feel it in my heart.
I feel thin.
Sort of stretched...
...like butter scraped
over too much bread.
I need a holiday. A very long holiday.
And I don't expect I shall return.
In fact, I mean not to.
Old Toby. The finest weed
in the Southfarthing.
Gandalf, my old friend...
...this will be a night to remember.
Hello, hello.
Fatty Bolger. Lovely to see you.
Welcome, welcome.
Go on, Sam. Ask Rosie for a dance.
-I think I'll just have another ale.
-Oh, no, you don't.
Go on!
So there I was...
...at the mercy
of three monstrous trolls.
And they were all arguing
amongst themselves...
...about how they were
going to cook us.
Whether it be turned on a spit, or to sit
on us one by one, squash us into jelly.
They spent so much time arguing
the whithertos and the whyfors...
...that the sun's first light
crept over the top of the trees...
...and turned them all to stone!
Quickly.
Up they go!
No, the big one.
Mrs. Bracegirdle, how nice to see you.
Welcome, welcome.
Are all these children yours?
Good gracious,
you have been productive.
Bilbo?
Sackville-Bagginses!
Quickly, hide!
Thank you, my boy.
You're a good lad, Frodo.
I'm very selfish, you know.
Yes, I am. Very selfish.
I don't know why I took you in after
your mother and father died...
...but it wasn't out of charity.
I think it was because...
...of all my numerous relations...
...you were the one Baggins
that showed real spirit.
Bilbo, have you been
at the Gaffer's home brew?
No.
Well, yes, but that's not the point.
The point is, Frodo...
...you'll be all right.
-Done!
-You're supposed to stick it in the ground.
-It is in the ground.
-Outside!
This was your idea.
Bilbo.
Bilbo, watch out for the dragon!
Nonsense. There hasn't been a dragon
in these parts for a thousand years.
-That was good.
-Let's get another one.
Meriadoc Brandybuck and Peregrin Took.
I might've known.
Speech, Bilbo!
Speech!
My dear Bagginses and Boffins...
...Tooks and Brandybucks...
...Grubbs, Chubbs...
...Hornblowers...
...Bolgers...
...Bracegirdles...
-...and Proudfoots.
-Proudfeet!
Today is my 111th birthday!
Happy birthday!
But alas, eleventh-one years is
far too short a time to live among...
...such excellent
and admirable Hobbits.
I don't know half of you
half as well as I should like...
...and I like less than half of you
half as well as you deserve.
I have things to do.
I've put this off far too long.
I regret to announce this is the end!
I'm going now.
I bid you all a very fond farewell.
Goodbye.
I suppose you think that was terribly clever.
Come on, Gandalf.
Did you see their faces?
There are many magic rings in this world,
and none of them should be used lightly.
It was just a bit of fun.
Oh, you're probably right, as usual.
-You will keep an eye on Frodo, won't you?
-Two eyes.
As often as I can spare them.
-I'm leaving everything to him.
-What about this ring of yours?
-Is that staying too?
-Yes, yes.
It's in an envelope over there
on the mantelpiece.
No. Wait, it's...
...here in my pocket.
Isn't that--? Isn't that odd, now?
Yet, after all, why not?
-Why shouldnt I keep it?
-I think you should leave the ring behind.
Is that so hard?
Well, no.
And yes.
Now it comes to it,
I don't feel like parting with it.
It's mine. I found it! It came to me!
-There's no need to get angry.
-Well, if I'm angry, it's your fault!
It's mine.
My own.
-My precious.
-Precious?
It's been called that before,
but not by you.
What business is it of yours
what I do with my own things?
I think you've had that ring
quite long enough.
-You want it for yourself!
-Bilbo Baggins!
Do not take me for some conjurer
of cheap tricks.
I am not trying to rob you.
I'm trying to help you.
All your long years,
we've been friends.
Trust me as you once did.
Let it go.
You're right, Gandalf.
The ring must go to Frodo.
It's late. The road is long.
Yes, it is time.
Bilbo, the ring is still in your pocket.
I've thought up an ending for my book:
"And he lived happily ever after
to the end of his days."
And I'm sure you will, my dear friend.
Goodbye, Gandalf.
Goodbye, dear Bilbo.
The road goes ever on and on
Until our next meeting.
It's mine. My own.
My precious.
Riddles in the dark.
Bilbo!
My precious.
Precious.
He's gone, hasn't he?
He talked for so long about leaving...
...I didn't think he'd really do it.
Gandalf?
Bilbo's ring.
He's gone to stay with the Elves.
He's left you Bag End.
Along with all his possessions.
The ring is yours now.
-Put it somewhere out of sight.
-Where are you going?
-There are some things that I must see to.
-What things?
-Questions. Questions that need answering.
-You've only just arrived.
I don't understand.
Neither do I.
Keep it secret.
Keep it safe.
Shire!
Baggins!
"The year 3434 of the Second Age.
Here follows the account of Isildur,
High King of Gondor...
...and the finding
of the Ring of Power."
"It has come to me.
The One Ring. It shall be
an heirloom of my kingdom.
All those who follow in my bloodline
shall be bound to its fate...
...for I will risk
no hurt to the Ring.
It is precious to me...
... though I buy it with great pain.
The markings upon the band
begin to fade.
The writing, which at first was as clear
as red flame, has all but disappeared.
A secret now
that only fire can tell."
Shire.
Baggins.
There's no Bagginses around here.
They're all up in Hobbiton.
That way.
To heal my heart and drown my woe
Rain may fall and wind may blow
But there still be
Many miles to go
Sweet is the sound of the pouring rain
And the stream that falls
From hill to plain
Better than rain or rippling brook
Is a mug of beer inside this Took
There's been some strange folk
crossing the Shire.
Dwarves and others of a less
than savory nature.
War is brewing.
The mountains are fair teeming
with goblins.
Far-off tales and childrens stories,
that's all that is.
You're beginning to sound like that old
Bilbo Baggins. Cracked, he was.
Young Mr. Frodo here,
he's cracking.
And proud of it.
-Cheers, Gaffer.
-Cheers.
It's none of our concern what goes on
beyond our borders.
Keep your nose out of trouble,
and no trouble'll come to you.
-Good night, lads.
-Good night.
Good night, sweet maiden
of the golden ale.
Mind who you're sweet-taking.
Don't worry, Sam. Rosie knows an idiot
when she sees one.
Does she?
-Good night, Sam.
-Good night, Mister Frodo.
Is it secret? Is it safe?
What are you doing?
Hold out your hand, Frodo.
It's quite cool.
What can you see?
Can you see anything?
Nothing.
There's nothing.
Wait.
There are markings.
It's some form of Elvish.
I can't read it.
There are few who can.
The language is that of Mordor,
which I will not utter here.
Mordor!
In the common tongue, it says:
"One Ring to rule them all...
...One Ring to find them...
...One Ring to bring them all...
...and in the darkness bind them."
This is the One Ring...
...forged by the Dark Lord Sauron
in the fires of Mount Doom.
Taken by IsiIdur
from the hand of Sauron himself.
Bilbo found it.
-In Gollum's cave.
-Yes.
For 60 years, the Ring lay quiet
in Bilbo's keeping...
...prolonging his life,
delaying old age.
But no longer, Frodo.
Evil is stirring in Mordor.
The Ring has awoken.
It's heard its master's call.
But he was destroyed.
Sauron was destroyed.
No, Frodo.
The spirit of Sauron endured.
His life force is bound to the Ring,
and the Ring survived.
Sauron has returned.
His Orcs have multiplied.
His fortress at Barad-dur
is rebuilt in the land of Mordor.
Sauron needs only this Ring to cover
all the lands in a second darkness.
He is seeking it.
Seeking it. All his thought
is bent on it.
For the Ring yearns above all else...
...to return to the hand
of its master.
They are one...
...the Ring and the Dark Lord.
Frodo...
...he must never find it.
All right.
We put it away. We keep it hidden.
We never speak of it again.
No one knows it's here, do they?
Do they, Gandalf?
There is one other who knew
that Bilbo had the Ring.
I looked everywhere
for the creature Gollum.
But the enemy found him first.
I don't know how long
they tortured him.
But amidst the endless screams and
babbleing they noticed two words.
Shire!
Baggins!
Shire.
Baggins.
But that would Iead them here!
Who goes there?
Take it, Gandalf!
-Take it!
-No, Frodo.
-You must take it!
-You cannot offer me this ring!
-I'm giving it to you!
-Don't tempt me, Frodo!
I dare not take it.
Not even to keep it safe.
Understand, Frodo...
...I would use this Ring
from a desire to do good.
But through me, it would wield a power
too great and terrible to imagine.
-But it cannot stay in the Shire!
-No.
No, it can't.
What must I do?
-You must leave. And leave quickly.
-Where? Where do I go?
Get out of the Shire.
Make for the village of Bree.
Bree.
-What about you?
-I'll be waiting for you...
...at the inn of the Prancing Pony.
-And the Ring will be safe there?
-I don't know, Frodo.
I don't have any answers.
I must see the head of my order. He is
both wise and powerful. Trust me, Frodo.
He'll know what to do.
You'll have to leave the name
of Baggins behind you.
That name is not safe
outside the Shire.
Travel only by day.
And stay off the road.
I can cut across country
easily enough.
My dear Frodo.
Hobbits really are amazing creatures.
You can learn all that there is to
know about their ways in a month.
And yet, after a hundred years...
...they can still surprise you.
Get down.
Confound it all, Samwise Gamgee!
Have you been eavesdropping?
I haven't been dropping no eaves. Honest.
I was cutting the grass under the window.
A little late for trimming the verge,
don't you think?
-I heard raised voices.
-What did you hear? Speak!
Nothing important.
That is, I heard a good deal about a ring,
a Dark Lord and the end of the world but--
Please, Mr. Gandalf, sir, don't hurt me.
Don't turn me into anything unnatural.
No?
Perhaps not.
I've thought of a better use for you.
Come along, Samwise. Keep up.
Be careful, both of you.
The enemy has many spies
in his service:
Birds, beasts.
Is it safe?
Never put it on...
...for the agents of the Dark Lord
will be drawn to its power.
Always remember, Frodo...
...the Ring is trying to get back
to its master.
It wants to be found.
This is it.
This is what?
If I take one more step...
...it'll be the farthest away
from home I've ever been.
Come on, Sam.
Remember what Bilbo used to say:
-"It's a dangerous business, Frodo."
-"Going out your door.
You step onto the road,
and if you don't keep your feet...
... there's no knowing where
you might be swept off to."
Sam.
Wood-elves.
They're going to the harbor
beyond the White Towers.
To the Grey Havens.
They're leaving Middle-earth.
Never to return.
I don't know why...
...it makes me sad.
Everywhere I lie there's a dirty
great root sticking into my back.
Just shut your eyes...
...and imagine you're back
in your own bed...
...with a soft mattress
and a lovely feather pillow.
It's not working, Mr. Frodo.
I'm never going to be able
to sleep out here.
Me neither, Sam.
Smoke rises
from the Mountain of Doom.
The hour grows late.
And Gandalf the Grey
rides to Isengard...
...seeking my counsel.
For that is why you have come,
is it not?
My old friend.
Saruman.
-You are sure of this?
-Beyond any doubt.
So the Ring of Power has been found.
All these long years,
it was in the Shire.
-Under my very nose.
-Yet you did not have the wit to see it.
Your love of the halfling's leaf
has clearly slowed your mind.
But we still have time. Time enough
to counter Sauron if we act quickly.
Time?
What time do you think we have?
Sauron has regained
much of his former strength.
He cannot yet take physical form...
...but his spirit has lost
none of its potency.
Concealed within his fortress,
the Lord of Mordor sees all.
His gaze pierces cloud, shadow,
earth and flesh.
You know of what I speak, Gandalf.
A Great Eye, lidless,
wreathed in flame.
The Eye of Sauron.
He is gathering all evil to him.
Very soon, he'll have summoned
an army...
...great enough for an assault
upon Middle-earth.
You know this?
How?
I have seen it.
A palantir is a dangerous tool,
Saruman.
Why?
Why should we fear to use it?
They are not all accounted for,
the lost Seeing-stones.
We do not know who else
may be watching.
The hour is later than you think.
Sauron's forces are already moving.
The Nine have left Minas Morgul.
The Nine?
They crossed the River Isen
on Midsummer's Eve...
...disguised as riders in black.
-They've reached the Shire?
-They will find the Ring.
And kill the one who carries it.
Frodo!
You did not seriously think that a Hobbit
could contend with the will of Sauron?
There are none who can.
Against the power of Mordor...
...there can be no victory.
We must join with him, Gandalf.
We must join with Sauron.
It would be wise, my friend.
Tell me...
...friend...
...when did Saruman the Wise
abandon reason for madness?
I gave you the chance...
...of aiding me willingly...
...but you have elected
the way of pain!
Mr. Frodo?
Frodo? Frodo!
-I thought I'd lost you.
-What are you taking about?
-It's just something Gandalf said.
-What did he say?
"Don't you lose him, Samwise Gamgee."
And I don't mean to.
Sam, we're still in the Shire.
What could possibly happen?
Frodo.
-Merry, it's Frodo Baggins.
-Hello, Frodo.
Get off him.
Come on, Frodo.
What's the meaning of this?
You've been into Farmer Maggot's crop!
You get back here!
Get out of my field!
You'll know the devil
if I catch up with you!
I don't know why he's so upset.
It's only a couple of carrots.
And some cabbages.
And those three bags of potatoes
that we lifted last week.
-And then the mushrooms the week before.
-Yes, Pippin. My point is...
...he's clearly overreacting.
Run!
Oh, that was close.
I think I've broken something.
Trust a Brandybuck and a Took!
What? That was just a detour.
A short cut.
-Short cut to what?
-Mushrooms!
That's mine.
That's nice, Merry.
Here's a nice one, Sam.
I think we should get off the road.
Get off the road!
Quick!
Be quiet!
What was that?
Anything?
Nothing.
What is going on?
That Black Rider was looking
for something. Or someone.
Frodo?
Get down!
I have to leave the Shire.
Sam and I must get to Bree.
Right.
Bucklebury Ferry. Follow me.
Run!
This way! Follow me!
Get the rope, Sam!
Frodo!
Run, Frodo!
Go!
-Hurry!
Frodo, come on!
-Come on! Faster!
-Jump!
-How far to the nearest crossing?
-The Brandywine Bridge. 20 miles.
Come on.
-What do you want?
-We're heading for the Prancing Pony.
Hobbits. Four Hobbits!
What's more, out of the Shire by your
talk. What business brings you to Bree?
We wish to stay at the inn.
Our business is our own.
All right, young sir.
I meant no offense.
It's my job to ask questions
after nightfall.
There's talk of strange folk abroad.
Can't be too careful.
Out of the way!
Watch where you're waking.
Excuse me.
Good evening, little masters.
What can I do for you?
If you're looking accommodation, we got
some cozy Hobbit-sized rooms available.
Always proud to cater
to the Little Folk, Mister...?
Underhill. My name's Underhill.
-Underhill, yes.
-We're friends of Gandalf the Grey.
-Can you tell him we've arrived?
-Gandalf?
Gandalf.
Oh, yes...
...I remember. Elderly chap.
Big grey beard, pointy hat.
Not seen him for six months.
What do we do now?
Sam...
...he'll be here. He'll come.
Get out of my way!
What's that?
This, my friend, is a pint.
It comes in pints?
-I'm getting one.
-You got a whole half already!
That fellow's done nothing
but stare at you since we arrived.
Excuse me.
That man in the corner. Who is he?
He's one of them Rangers. They're
dangerous folk, wandering the Wilds.
What his right name is, I've never heard,
but around here he's known as Strider.
Strider.
Baggins.
Baggins? Sure, I know a Baggins.
He's over there. Frodo Baggins.
He's my second cousin,
once removed on his mother's side...
...and my third cousin, twice removed....
-Pippin!
-Steady on, Frodo.
You cannot hide.
I see you.
There is no life...
...in the void.
Only...
...death.
You draw far too much attention
to yourself, "Mr. Underhill."
What do you want?
A little more caution from you.
That is no trinket you carry.
-I carry nothing.
-Indeed.
I can avoid being seen if I wish...
...but to disappear entirely,
that is a rare gift.
-Who are you?
-Are you frightened?
Yes.
Not nearly frightened enough.
I know what hunts you.
Let him go!
Or I'll have you, Longshanks.
You have a stout heart, little Hobbit.
But that will not save you.
You can no longer wait
for the wizard, Frodo.
They're coming.
What are they?
They were once Men.
Great kings of Men.
Then Sauron the Deceiver gave to them
nine rings of power.
Blinded by their greed,
they took them without question.
One by one, falling into darkness.
Now they are slaves to his will.
They are the Nazgul.
Ringwraiths. Neither living nor dead.
At all times they feel...
... the presence of the Ring...
...drawn to the power of the One.
They will never stop hunting you.
-Where are you taking us?
-Into the Wild.
How do we know this Strider
is a friend of Gandalf?
I think a servant of the enemy
would look fairer...
-...and feel fouler.
-He's foul enough.
We have no choice but to trust him.
-But where is he leading us?
-To Rivendell, Master Gamgee.
-To the house of Elrond.
-Did you hear that? Rivendell.
We're going to see the Elves.
-Gentlemen, we do not stop till nightfall.
-What about breakfast?
-You've already had it.
-We've had one, yes.
What about second breakfast?
Don't think he knows
about second breakfast, Pip.
What about elevenses? Luncheon?
Afternoon tea? Dinner? Supper?
-He knows about them, doesn't he?
-I wouldnt count on it.
Pippin!
What do they eat
when they can't get Hobbit?
Who is she?
This woman you sing of.
'Tis the lady of Luthien.
The EIf-maiden who gave her love
to Beren, a mortal.
What happened to her?
She died.
Get some sleep, Frodo.
The power of Isengard
is at your command...
... Sauron, Lord of the Earth.
Build me an army worthy of Mordor.
What orders from Mordor, my lord?
What does the Eye command?
We have work to do.
The trees are strong, my lord.
Their roots go deep.
Rip them all down.
This was the great watchtower
of Amon Sul.
We shall rest here tonight.
These are for you.
Keep them close.
I'm going to have a look around.
Stay here.
My tomato's burst.
Could I have some bacon?
Want a tomato, Sam?
-What are you doing?!
-Tomatoes, sausages, nice crispy bacon.
-We saved some for you, Mr. Frodo.
-Put it out, you fools!
-Put it out!
-That's nice! Ash on my tomatoes!
Go!
Back, you devils!
Frodo!
Oh, Sam.
Strider!
-Help him, Strider.
-He's been stabbed by a Morgul blade.
This is beyond my skill to heal.
He needs Elvish medicine.
Hurry!
We're six days from Rivendell!
He'll never make it!
Hold on, Frodo.
Gandalf!
Look, Frodo. It's Mr. Bilbo's trolls.
Mr. Frodo? He's going cold.
Is he going to die?
He's passing into the Shadow World.
He'll soon become a Wraith like them.
-They're close.
-Sam, do you know the Athelas plant?
-Athelas?
-Kingsfoil.
Kingsfoil, aye, it's a weed.
It may help to slow the poisoning.
Hurry!
What's this?
A Ranger caught off his guard?